you'd like to begin now yeah i'm uh here
with jordan hall
who has been a fascinating voice online
and in a lot of different circles who
are interested in processing
what they call sense making in this new
time that we're in
he's been talking about the shift
in how we should process things and the
shift in our
institutions and then of course with
this pandemic
that conversation is even more pressing
and more
on the minds of people so thanks for
coming on the program jordan
yeah nice to nice to be here so what's
your background though and how did you
get involved in this these these topics
that you've been
online about people are watching you and
they're seeing you engage with other
thinkers like-minded folks trying to
think ahead of the curve and
see what's coming along that the human
species needs to get prepared for
but where how did you start on this
train of thought
um well i suppose maybe this to me keep
it compact to keep it simple
um you might say that i'm a
uh i'm a dilettante well
or polymath depending on your preference
and i have an attraction to
a certain class of kind of thinking and
also kind of doing
so in the context of thinkers the names
that came up we were just just before we
started recording we were talking about
mcluhan
so you might see that i'm a an applied
and applied mcluhanite
but equally john boyd is somebody who
i've been very influenced by
which is optimal when applied
um another philosopher manuel delanda
i've also been very attracted to his
work
um there's a few more you could throw in
but if you kind of get the spread of
those kinds of individuals
you know i just i like to read and
always have and was reading those
those kinds of thinkers relatively young
that's one side and the other side when
i say applied i mean applied so i
actually
was involved in three startup companies
that went public
in the latter part of the 20th century
earlier part of the 21st century
all in the context of decentralized
media
so the first was called np3.com if you
recall music
the second was a company called
interview which ultimately was purchased
by
a company called akamai which you may be
familiar with
and the third was called divex which
played a major role in
making the internet a visual medium so
all this video that we're doing whether
it's watching youtube videos or
doing zoom calls was uh uh
kicked into gear at least meaningfully
by the work that we were doing
um and and it's sort of a way of getting
a sense of it
i think in 2004 maybe 2003
kind of in the middle of my my divex arc
um i bought
two two books from manuel de landa
and gave copies to like 150 people
uh including my entire uh executive team
so it's a good sense of like this notion
of having a uh
a copy of uh de lloys and qatari
on my lap as i was sitting in the
waiting room to talk to
um sergey brin about google making an
offer to buy my company so that
combination because kind of those
that that sensibility that's probably a
pretty good concrete sitting
in the lobby waiting to go talk to
sergey about buying div x
um while reading um maybe it was just a
lawyers maybe it was a difference in
repetition i can't remember exactly but
you kind of get the gist so that kind of
that's a that's a nice compact example
that gives you the the sensibility of it
um maybe one last piece is i'm currently
actually sitting on my family's
hilltop ranch in the texas hill country
um and we've been spending roughly half
my time in what you might call thinking
and mostly these days actually turning a
lot of the thinking that's been going
over the past 10 years into
strategic planning around what might be
trajectories from now
uh and the other half you know planting
raised bed gardens and
moving limestone rocks from one place to
another place so you're homesteading and
all that kind of thing huh
yeah and that's not a new thing we
actually have an actual homestead
and is there a particular reason for
that just
because of where you think things are
heading or just because of the pleasure
and the desire to live that that kind of
lifestyle the pleasure and desire to
live that kind of lifestyle
good but that's that's do you think that
all human beings should live
close to that if not doing it directly
but being
close to people who are homesteading and
providing products and
milk the word large
logical category right do you think it's
natural for human beings to go into
subterranean cattle cars and be shifted
back and forth into big cities where
they're
you know definitely not natural i would
go further to say it's also prob
almost certainly not healthy right um so
if i were to say
like the way i would say it is more like
almost everyone
and for a sizable fracture in the time
should be doing the kinds of things
that are part of the evolutionary arc
of humans so staring at the fire
um instead of staring electric lights
for example
and touching earth and planting things
and being
in sync with the the rhythms of weather
like you should know what
what the weather's like outside without
checking an app on your phone those are
i think good heuristics i think very
much in terms of heuristics and not in
terms of uh
um categorical structures right do you
see
that uh do you see a similar uh
dynamic going on with what peter thiel
talks about in terms of
you know we've had this great stagnation
since the 1970s and
you know after we did the man on the
moon the last uh the last
moon mission we kind of seemed like we
just
stalled and we've become more interested
in innovating in the world of what he
calls
bits rather than atoms uh that all that
you know when we think of technological
progress it's always in the world of ai
or computer apps rather than in physical
innovation and because of that great
stagnation in atoms
that's why we're in this kind of state
of madness that we're in where we're
we're we don't know how to get along
anymore and we don't know how to
uh you know process conflict in healthy
ways do you see that dynamic
yeah sure in fact to be very specific um
i
i've known eric weinstein for gosh
almost 15 years now something like that
some significant amount of time before
he met peter and um i used to
to simplify things by just saying 1977.
that's obviously hyper simplistic but
yeah very much very much so there's a
line somewhere in the 70s
where something very significant changed
and so yes i am i i would put a lot of
chips on that bed right
well that's what i think and i think
there's a connection there with
uh you know the ending of the bretton
woods system you know with this idea of
getting us off the last
link to gold that nixon did that there's
this for sure there's this rise
in this uh you know central bank managed
economy that's going to become the new
uh you know experiment that will take
place
worldwide and i think that has some
correlation to the stagnation and real
wage growth and so on that has been
seemingly a kind of sticking point for
for our culture where
we're starting to start to point fingers
at each other we're dividing based on
gender
and race and so forth and this notion
that if you cannot
markets can't really function if you
don't allow them to truly
expand and grow and when they become
kind of
uh a zombie market that's propped up by
central bank and financial institutions
that are just
kind of creating this consumer uh
consumption based economy rather than
real
i guess atomistic creation like we used
to have
you're going to have this moment where
we feel rich and we feel decadent but
there is a real shrinking pie at the
real tangible
you know point of of living you know
there's a real
there's a real through energy
there's a whole lot that we could do in
that zone you can go all kinds of ways
in that direction
um so yeah inside
there's a lot there's a lot there um you
can think about
maybe a very deep piece is the
the ungroundedness in general and
groundness of culture in general
one aspect of which is the
ungroundedness of money
but the ungroundedness of culture in
general and um
and the the capacity and in some sense
the tendency
of culture and individual psychology to
what's the word the trans humans used to
wirehead or to become delusional
right when you when you are ungrounded
um you know when you have the ability
to take cocaine and to feel like you're
you've got tiger blood um
we're talking about yeah yeah but i was
trying to reference
charlie's jeans yeah but i was just
thinking about tiger king everybody's
watching tiger king thinking they're
living a great life as their whole
country's design reality isn't actually
working out exactly and i would say
from a mcluhan perspective the rise of
tv
has an interesting correlation like you
know the the nixon
financial disconnect and also the
amount of time that our minds were
living in a fantasy land
of stroboscopic light and increasingly
stereoscopic sound
there's a correlation though there's two
pieces connect and they're not
they're cor they're they're correlated
right they're not strictly a causal but
they begin to build a fabric
of a capacity to become increasingly
disconnected
from base reality from the ground and
there's a bunch of feedback leaps that
happen when that can occur
you're mentioning some of the thinkers
that you have been influenced by
one of the individuals that i've tried
to
try to popularize in my columns and in
my radio and podcast
work is rene gerard the anthropologist
from stanford
uh have you engaged his work and have
you seen some insights there that have
been helpful for your ability to look at
this culture and this technology i have
although and i have to laugh because as
you probably at this point is
pretty self-evident to me that you're
you're somewhat familiar with peter
um you know one of peter's
instincts and ethos is contrarianism and
i would say that i am a i am a gerard
contrarian
and that's that's really just to say
that um i embed
gerard's insight into a larger complex
of
the current best thinking around for
example human development both
evolutionarily development and
individual development child child
development psychology
um and so my friend zach stein actually
i think has got the best
thinking on this because he's a really
an expert in development
and he's gone very deep to
um a way of putting it is something like
the memetic desire is a real thing but
it's
part of a larger complex of
psychological social cultural
evolutionary game theoretic constructs
uh and you can't if you put your thumb
on that scale
just like you're putting thumb on any
scale you're gonna end up getting a
little bit confused if you're not aware
of it you're also gonna be a little bit
confused
so that that's the way i look at it it's
interesting so
would you say it also has a physics
component this the the same process that
that manifests as mimetic desire as you
you said there's an evolutionary there's
a
psychological component to it that's
deeper than just the
the surface of imitation of desires
would there be a physical component to
it too
well the the answer to your question is
i've never thought that thought before
but when you put it in my mind it feels
like a very fun thought to think so
i'd be very interested in contemplating
it or chatting about it
yeah it's something that i've been
thinking about a lot
is this idea that if if you do see this
symmetry of you know desired and you see
it
you're right it's not just in human
desire you look at
animals and the symmetries of conflict
and mating and this
this little pattern that you see yep it
looks like there it may go all the way
down to the subatomic level that there's
this
built-in mechanism that we express and
we we talk about it as
desire uh but it it actually looks
a lot more fundamental to me than a word
like desire
this is real interesting i i don't know
how much as a
a matter of content if your show kind of
goes into the
the deeply esoteric but we can that's
the rabbit hole i'd dive in
real quick sure yeah there's a lot so
so one of the ways that i that i've
thought about it and
this is i'm basically just applying a
framework that i've used in the past
that seems like it might roughly fit
um not to over code the the domain where
app
maybe to get some some directions maybe
get some orientation on it
is this is a distinction that i've made
between what i'm
what i call the rivalries and the
anti-rivalries
which maps roughly to atoms and bits
as it turns out um which by the way we
should be very clear the third term here
which you might consider energy
to be a a process or a dynamic
between the two um so atoms bits and
energy
feels like that's a pretty solid uh
constellation and
you know the characteristic of the
rivalrous is that is rivalry
desire competitive desire the fact that
at the end of the day there are certain
aspects of the physical universe of
which physics is largely the thing the
branch of science that studies that
universe um that are are
at the bottom strictly not uh shareable
both in the sense that they are atomic
meaning
if you have it i don't have it in some
sense
uh and and and tropic i mean that that
to the degree to which you interact with
it in any way you turn
the free energy into entropy you've
depleted it permanently in a one-way
direction
so there are certain aspects of the
universe the things that are studied by
physics
that have those characteristics and
around those aspects you would imagine
that they would evolve
for example a as a fundamental
characteristic of any
system that sorry i have to back up
there's
another component here which has to do
with the irreducible necessity of the
ability to accumulate an up gradient of
that particular scarce fundamental
scarce aspect of reality in order to
perpetuate dissipative systems
right so we have another thing here
which is i think you just channeled
there for a second i see that
yeah well that was a terrible say that
you might think i was i was trying to
think real deep
oh yeah no that's good uh the way this
is actually a secret but i'm
i'm i'm pretty much a synesthete and i
don't actually think in words
um and so when i'm doing that
what i'm actually doing is trying to
hold a particular
i kind of refer to as a geometry but
it's almost a little bit more like
you ever seen those puzzles that are a
3d puzzle that you're looking at on a
computer screen so it's 2d
right yeah you have to rotate it and
orient it until the 3d system
pops and you see the 3d model yeah a
little bit like that like i'm actually
moving things in some i don't know some
interior space
but once it locks then i have to hold it
because it's not easy to hold but once i
hold it then i have to start figuring
how to pull the words out that
map to the thing but the thing is the
thing um
and that may very well be what's
referred to as channeling
but yeah that was that little bit right
there was a nice chunk of stuff
i'm reasonably confident and um
okay so you've got that you've got
dissipative systems and you've got the
the reality that there's essentially a
binary in dissipative systems which is
to say that either they
are what de lois would call his cities
you might mean a simple term would be
ephemeral like a uh
a sirocco or a little breeze you know it
comes around
and it goes away and so it evaporates
and then there are others
that have a capacity to pull
resources from their external
environment which now by definition
are going to be rivalrous resources to
perpetuate their being what they are
a pattern that has the capacity to
repeat itself over time i'm pulling a
lot of
uh right now a lot of deloitte's and to
a lesser extent to launder into that
so you know this by the way i had this
conversation with brett weinstein
uh about 12 years ago we kind of were
discussing ethics we got down to the
very bottom which is
okay we can we can make a proposition
that we have
a habit of thought which is based on a
simple survivor's bias
we happen to be the leading edge of a
13.7 billion year survivor's bias
of those set that tiny subset of all
possible phenomena
that didn't just evaporate back into the
quantum phone
um and then you know so then started
getting atoms and the atoms became
molecules and didn't evaporate back into
the atomic
you know maelstrom and the molecules
became organic molecules didn't just
evaporate back right so that
structural development where's this we
have the survivor's bias of that and
you know kind of channel a little bit of
jordan peterson here if you plug him
into that structure you're like yeah
and the narratives and mytho poetics and
ethos and values that we happen to have
sitting
you know that we sit on top of are an
expression of that entire arc
of which now we can plug the medic
desire is a
real deep piece of that which probably
goes all the way
down to the struggle between um
quarks to be the ones that actually turn
into atoms
right there that pivot point between to
be and not to be
or to continue to be to become on in
becoming
or to become nothingness again is
probably the the pivot point
um and if you anchor there pull all the
way back out you can hold continuity
from the quantum foam all the way up to
you know complex cultures i think then
you've got a very fair frame to actually
start really talking about
the gerardian insight but to remember
that you're holding
that piece of reality which is the piece
of reality that's talking about the
rival risk talking about these
characteristics of
of the sort of things that physics
studies but then we have to talk about
the the other side
which has to do with um
creativity emergence and this is where
eric and i
have still never yet finished i figured
out how to figure out our knife fight
and brett i think sits in the in the
middle of it because he at the end of
the day as an evolutionary theorist
cannot dispense with the notion of of
evolution he can't dispense with the
notion that there is in fact
change that the the the the sort of
newtonian or nothing turn in the
i call the simple einsteinian model of a
all
one static space-time continuum you know
the notion that there is in fact
no novelty that all has in some sense
happen instantaneously and that
to the degree to which we perceive
change it's an illusion
from an evolutionary theory perspective
that isn't
a good a good model an evolutionary
theorist has to have at least some
notion
that you can actually you actually can
go from zero to one
you can go from what is to an entirely
novel in some
in time some kind of actual novelty like
innovation
novation exists as a part of ontology
well okay that's the other piece right
novation
cannot be strictly rivalrous because at
the very beginning you're literally
going from zero to one you were in fact
creating moreness
that piece is the piece that is
not fully captured in
purely mimetic desire because you you're
actually creating something new there is
no copy there
so that would be the other the other
piece that i would layer in to get a
fully rich
uh theory so you've got things you've
got things like scarcity
and then this idea of maybe post
scarcity here or this idea like
i'm thinking of the um the biblical
story of jesus when he's
handing out the fishes and loaves and he
takes these fishes and loaves but
they just keep coming he doesn't cut he
doesn't cut the fish up into pieces
right everybody get a little out little
meat here no he's just like nope
and it's this this declaration of war
against scarcity
right and it doesn't require it doesn't
require
coercion to do he doesn't he doesn't say
all right i've i'm forcing you to give
me your
food he just the voluntary exchange and
from that voluntary exchange
there's this renunciation of the
confining
power of scarcity right well i mean
that's creativity without conflict right
that's create that it's that's
creativity that's
generativity and as you notice there's a
whole bunch of characteristics like if
you think about that particular
uh parable there's a a mentality
there's a premise there's a commitment
to peace
for example you can't in fact have
generativity outside of peace
peace is the space which gives rise to
the possibility of true collaboration
once you've achieved peace you then have
achieved this capacity to shift
from a scarcity dynamic to an abundance
dynamic
um plenitude as a
secondary artifact and i'm making that
distinction so
i think of i think of there being a uh a
scarcity mentality
in it attached to the scarcity mentality
and we can actually use shifting to the
myth of poetic
i would tag the character of mammon so
mammon is what happens when you operate
with the scarcity mentality
but multiply by grotesquery so you know
the jabba the hutt character drop of the
hut is has
as uh too much but still is tied to a
scarcity of mentality and is trying to
plug the whole of scarcity through
getting more
that's the wrong answer then you've got
another thing over here which we can
talk about uh jesus and
the parable which is to say no we're
actually going to move into the
abundance mentality
we're going to move into a space that is
anchored in a fundamental sense of
orienting towards this other domain the
domain of creativity domain of
generativity
the domain of novation which first and
foremost has to be held in a space of
peace
but once we're in that space we
recognize that we're now in a place this
place of plenitude
which doesn't necessarily even vaguely
look like jabba the hutt and it actually
looks nothing at all like that
it's like a whole bunch of people who
have actually have to be conscious of
the fact that
to maintain the integrity of peace is
the first thing you have to do
that's the beginning if you can't
maintain the integrity of peace then the
whole plenitude evaporates and so
therefore each of us as an individual
has to start taking responsibility for
only taking that piece of the peace
that is ours and to carry the cross that
desires to carry fully and completely
to maintain the integrity of that you
know that thing is the most sacred the
most sacrosanct
um yeah sorry i think it would have
been a tie right there no but it's this
idea that
you don't have to divide up the pieces
that you have that you can take
what you have and through voluntary
sharing
you can uh you can alleviate
the the pressures of a scarce world that
you've got a whole crowd here who's
hungry
who's going to get fed first that's the
question you'd immediately think
is it going to be the uh apostles or is
it going to be
those who are richest in the crowd who
have fast passes to disney world
who's it going to be and this issue
is not resolved by saying okay let's
let's ration out what we have we've got
a basket of fish and loaves
somehow in that moment of voluntary
sharing
scarcity is just overcome it's just it's
the scarcity is just thrown out the
window as if it doesn't actually bind up
the universe after all
well it's a lot of powerful stuff in
there too because if you think about it
there's a moment
there's a choice and a big part of that
choice has to do with fear
you know if you're able to choose
in the face of fear because at that
moment they'll say hey
who's going to get the scarce fish
and loads and maybe if i'm if i'm
fearful if i allow fear to be my
my basis of choice then i'll i'll
struggle
to be the one who either a gets it or
even better gets to be the one who makes
the
determination i want to be the boss if
there's going to be a boss i want to be
the boss i just don't want to be the
boss as crony
um you have to get past that you have to
find a way to get past that that
as the basis of choice and it's a very
this is a very nuanced thing i'm saying
i don't mean be foolhardy i don't mean
numb yourself to the reality of the
possibility of privation
what i mean is to not allow that to be
the basis of your choice to go deeper
than that
not to to to to ignore it but actually
to recognize that it's a real thing it's
a fundamental thing it's a part of
reality
but it's not the fun most fundamental
part of reality below that
deeper than that is that sense of well
this particular parable would be love
which is deeper than fear
and if you can anchor in that then you
begin to recognize that oh oh
if we voluntarily associate in this
space of peace
we can in fact get past this problem
this necessity
to begin competing with who's going to
be the boss and who's going to be the
crony of the boss and most importantly
who's going to eat who's not going to
eat and it has always been thus right so
if you think about it as a
as a narrative of the human experience
it's just
trying to remind us of the fact that
when we move ourselves into a mindset of
scarcity when we move
are moved from a basis of fear we may
believe that we have solved a problem
but we in fact have bitten off the
biggest problem of all which will never
inevitably end now now we're in gerard
land we've
anchored ourselves deeply in gerard land
we know how that story ends
um and therefore we must always be
mindful of the necessity of choosing not
to go there
the necessity of choosing even when it
is at its most challenging
to be anchored in that sense of love to
create the space of peace to voluntarily
associate
and from there is the only path that
leads us into
a good future so you know that's where
it's a little bit
uh ambiguous with gerard because he
points out that
scarcity is often the occasion for
scapegoating
there's that word the elephant in the
room the scapegoating the sacrificial
violence
that communities have used to create
peace
and order and he's good about that word
remembrance we're remembering the body
and our primordial past that we have
torn asunder to create that peace that
that we can have skin in the game but
it'll be somebody else's skin in the
game that binds us together
that's where we get the word religion
that latin root is to bind together what
are we binding together
we're binding together a community
around a shared corpse a shared
at the earliest levels uh cannibalism
eating devouring your
eating someone's body and drinking their
blood which uh unfortunately
is at the root of a lot of of the
records of human
uh culture so you know
when i think about that um
jordan did we lose you no i'm just
thinking really hard
okay uh we're in a space right now where
where it
behooves us to be thinking really yeah
yeah yeah well the what i'm trying to
suggest is is uh
you know this idea that uh
that scarcity triggers this sacrificial
devouring that we do and we're doing it
we're still doing it doesn't it doesn't
give us the peace anymore
as gerard said the jesus story comes
into history and disrupts
our ability to unanimously come together
around who should be the villain and who
should be devoured
now we can't agree we're still trying
the scapegoat mechanism
but it's not providing the the heroin
it's not providing the high
it's not providing the bound up
togetherness that we used to have
it's creating ever more schism the more
we try that old trick that
give me that old-time religion remember
that song yeah
we're trying that old-time religion
everywhere don't you
yeah we're trying spend a little bit of
time in the twitter verse
yeah yeah they're always who can we
cancel today and they're trying so
hard but they're never going to get it
back it can't become a bad guy
yeah because the the christ the christ
story has destroyed that
that trick that rabbit trick has been
destroyed it hasn't destroyed the
appetite for it though
that appetite's still there because
we're we're
we're we're are yeah can i throw
something else on top
so let's pivot let's pivot from the
mythopoetic for a second and pivot back
to the
not the real concrete the uh
oppenheimer also destroyed it
war got real complicated in 1945.
it used to be that uh you know we would
look
collectively at the bodies of the dead
in our war our shared sacrifice
and will if we had purged exhausted the
energy of the conflict in the blood
in this case almost universally for
quite some time over the 20th century at
least of the
young men who died in the trenches
around about 1945 we found ourselves in
a very uncomfortable situation
where we got right up to the threshold
and had this thing looking back at us
called mutually assured destruction
we had to start figuring out how to
shift the boundary conditions of
how we exercise that that impulse the
impulse of
you the impulse to punch you in the
face or hit you with a rock right
um i think there's a finding that's very
powerful like it's that that's an
embodiment of the christ myth in in a
in a sense right i think i've said this
on a previous conversation i think with
jack murphy which
for was 000 years we had a story where
we were invited to live in a certain way
for the past 100 years we've had a story
where we actually we have to figure out
how to
we've got no choice and every day the
how would i call it the pit gets wider
and deeper and closer to our toes
in 1945 just well it's making 1962
jess khrushchev and kennedy could have
plunged the world into nuclear abyss
just two guys and all they had to do is
not push the button
but every day in every way we just get
better and better at killing everybody
which means we got to get better and
better at not killing everybody and that
that that age-old 13.5 billion year
habit
of when push comes to shove pushing and
shoving we have to actually figure out
how to not do that we have to actually
learn how to anchor ourselves in that
space of peace
to consistently and always as as
individuals and as a collective to make
that choice to freely associate
um and it's right there it's just i feel
like we
we sort of if we if we step back and
just sort of look at it we can tell
that we're currently right now living in
two worlds simultaneously
you can feel the energy of the of the
gerardian
conflict yeah the scarcity mentality
that any moment wants to just tear apart
the whole story pardon me and
on the other hand the other side
salvation
well that's the question that i was you
know because the ambiguous part that i
was alluding to is the idea that well
yes
scarcity tends to be the occasion for
the impulse to
find a scapegoat to resolve the tension
if there's a famine
if there's a plague if there's lack of
resources
if there's a murder spree whatever it is
something creates scarcity scarcity of
life scarcity of food scarcity of
existence scarcity of
of order scarcity of resources scarcity
of health
and that triggers this hunt for the
scapegoat so we're still trying that
today but my question is that some
people would suggest
and there's a quote i think it's
i think it's dostoevsky or someone that
says basically that
if we would resolve all scarcity issues
if we could resolve all material want
would human beings stop their conflict
and it's like no there's something about
human beings that
you could meet all their needs and they
would still find ways to
create eternal drama so that's my
question is is it really
i i rack my mind about this all the time
because i'm always on the hunt for
things that could provide
solutions for scarcity and i think about
all right
let's find energy too cheap to meter
that's abundant you know what would that
do to alleviate the social pressures
to attack everybody based on collective
identities and
nations and bombings and all these
things would that would that
would that reduce it a little bit and
then what if we could have
uh you know cures for cancer and
alzheimer's and diabetes and all these
terrible things that our people are
stressed out about they have this
latent death anxiety and that bothers
them knowing that people they love
around them
will have these afflictions that don't
really seem to have any resolution or
cure
imagine we could just cure all those
different things in our lifetime
so we cure pollution we cure energy
scarcity we cure
uh diseases that have been afflicting
and scaring us
would we still have the same level of
conflict or would it reduce it
that there is job of the hut all right
that that's the thing where the thing
that's actually the problem which is the
fear at your heart
right so to be the basis of your choice
is fundamentally anchored in fear
and you try to solve that by endeavoring
to extinguish scarcity in the outside
and you you create um
a cornucopia of of muchness
and you and you've actually not solved
the problem even the least bit
you haven't stepped it product in many
ways you actually get more fearful in in
the core
um and there's another way right the the
other way
is to sort of recognize that the only
zero to one
the only real bit that flips the only
real change that could ever happen
is at that basis of choice
how much are you are you able to have
the basis of choice the thing that is at
the bottom of how it is you're coming
into the choices you're making how much
are you able to achieve coming into that
place from the space of of love or peace
or grace whatever term you'd like to use
and they're all
all part of the same complex that can't
really be named or fear
or sin right that's it
because you know and we have plenty of
stories of people who've been able to
make that shift
if you come from that place of love and
you perceive a possibility of material
scarcity real scarcity
the way you relate to that real scarcity
is just completely different
contrary wise if you come from a place
of fear and you're sitting in a world of
absolute plenitude you're still an
asshole
you can't help it greed will still drive
a lot of your choice making
so the question is how
deeply can you ground yourself in that
other place
and it doesn't mean for the least bit
you're going to get rid of the aspect of
reality that is bounded by
thermodynamics
and that's still a fundamental
characteristic of reality what it means
is that your choice making
will not be dominated by that
characteristic of reality
your choice making will first and
foremost be coming from this other
location and it will be
you know now we're back to the loaves
and fishes right as a parable
your choice making will always be saying
let us think more
deeply let us consider more fully how it
is we may find a way to achieve
abundance in this space if we can
maintain the capacity
to not be at each other's throats now
we're 13.6 billion years into this game
we've got a lot of instincts that are
oriented towards scarcity
um it'll probably be another 13.6
billion years before we can be so fully
anchored in the other side of that
equation that we can feel like it's a
real
forever all all the time but
there's definitely a sort of a 50 50.
how often are your choices coming from
one place to the other
how aware are you of what's the basis of
your choice to what degree are you
unconsciously acting
at a scarcity to what degree are you
able to say oh sorry about that
i just made a choice out of this place
how well can you come back
into this new basis how well can you
recover when you get
kind of knocked off your path can you
say oh i'm off the path and before i do
anything else because if i'm off the
path most of my choices are probably
going to create
harm before i do anything how do i get
back on the path how do i what is it the
12 steps how do i um
i can't remember what the third step is
but it's somewhere in the direction of
how do i
atone for my for my the trespasses that
i've made against others
while i've been unconscious while i've
been off the path that's just
skillfulness right it's not that
different in some sense from learning
how to juggle
not easy but you can do it and once
you've done it it doesn't mean you're
perfect it doesn't mean like if you're
juggling and somebody comes and shoves
you that you're not going to drop the
balls
but it does mean that you can do
something there's a skillfulness and the
capacity
to orient yourself towards this basis of
choice anchored in
grace and love become more and more
capable of staying
in that place and knowing when you're
out of it and always knowing how to come
back to it
and then of course in that place
everyone who has that skillfulness has a
capacity to be in relationship with
everyone else who has that skillfulness
that is oriented towards generativity
and that is the basis of true plenitude
and this is i think this is the real
conflict the real competition
there's a competition between the
instincts that is are oriented towards
scarcity
which is to say well first and foremost
i want to be the boss
and i want to make everybody else be my
cronie from something called the rules
for rulers
well go ahead what's that the real is
really good case study of the logic of
scarcity
and how important how how fearful
uh a dictator must be of of their
the people who are directly underneath
them because of course no human can ever
rule
a tribe of people at the end of the day
each of us are just one person
it's only people allowing themselves to
be ruled and they allow themselves to be
ruled in a series
of surrendering their sovereignty and so
if you're the
boss you're the boss by virtue of the
of the five to ten people who directly
are underneath you that's the people
right underneath you who are your
enforcers
and perhaps your your your operators and
your organizers
each one of them looks at each other as
a rival it's rivalry at the top
more so than anything else but if you're
good at what you do you can use the
rules for rulers and keep things hanging
together
and maintain yourself and your cabal as
being at the top of the scarcity pyramid
and of course you want to make
absolutely certain that everybody at the
bottom of the scarcity pyramid
is also making a local game theoretic
choice
to not pull together with anybody else
at the bottom of that pyramid
lest you be overthrown so that's the
game right the game on that on that side
of the equation the game based on the
basis of fear
is that game how do i maintain myself on
my cabal at the top of the scarcity
pyramid
and how do i manage that pyramid pyramid
by through hooker by crook
i can lie i can bribe think about how
saudi arabia manages its population
and it's got a small cabal of people who
are aristocrats on top
and they got lots of resources so they
just make sure that they may
make the people fear violence enough
and appreciate uh seek violence little
enough
that they stay uh a well-managed herd
they stay in in the cattle zone of
humans and then
you know and the pyramid maintains right
that's one structure
and of course it's a it's a structure
that we've seen for a long time that's
the domain of the sacred you just
described
the the idea that's the domain of the
sacred that
that sacred violence staves off profane
violence right
and so it's so that's the second the
second one is where sacred violence
staves off profane violence right the
first one is fear of profane violence
maintains a a tacit agreement to stay in
the profane
and a big piece of the profane
is to simulate and also to parasitize
the sacred
think about the movie star wars you
ready i'm gonna go straight 1970s kid
for you
old george lucas did a a a terrible and
horrible and wonderful thing at the same
time
he uh tapped into
joseph campbell and he crafted a parable
tapping into our mythopoetic sacred at
the deep roots of sacred
which every child who watched that movie
was like oh okay that
you know my instincts that have been
born through a lot of countless
generations
trying to sense what is right and what
is wrong that story resonates with it by
the way i look around me watching uh
saturday morning cartoons and tv
commercials i don't see much of it so
even though it's a thin gruel of
mythopoetic sacredness it's more more
than nothing
and then he proceeded and with the good
help of the folks at disney even more so
to strip mine the sacred as maximally as
possible to feed
the job of the hut character in the
profane and make us lose sight of the
difference between the sacred and the
prophet
but there is a difference right the
other side is the sacred violence
the other side is the the
not rules for rulers voluntary
association we've got a goddamn term for
it
people actually recognizing that to come
together um
entirely voluntarily out of wisdom
out of a felt sense of the reality of
community
that we are in fact all part of the
brotherhood of man it is inevitable it
has always been thus we are family in a
deep sense
now i don't mean that artificially i
mean that really to actually do it and
you know
going back to homesteading you get 10
strangers
and you have them build something
together and have them live or die by
the
by the virtues of their own hands and
nine of them
will actually become family typically
one of them will still buy
kind of a an asshole not necessarily but
you got to keep your eye out for that
one
because that's part of the story as well
right so i think that we can continue to
tap on that
that distinction between the sacred and
the profane the distinction between
the fear-based scarcity mentality
not scarcity itself but the mentality
that is using fear to maintain its
if one of us is going to starve it's
going to be you and the
you know the state of grace of being in
the abundance mentality which says well
neither of us needs to starve if we work
together
right as long as we stay in that that
scarcity driven mindset will cling to
uh the failing drug of sacrificial
violence through the form of political
violence and
coercion and so forth i mean and all of
its all of its uh ancillaries
self-delusion in fact straight-up drugs
we've got plenty of them in this in the
body of this society
yeah i do think it's an obvious
correlation between
this this it's weird how there's this
you know you you get this idea that
uh some folks will say you know on the
right even
you know liberalism or libertarianism is
the failure of our culture
this idea of individual rights or my
individualism
and uh autonomous individuals and i
think to myself wait a second
libertarians don't have any power that's
not their fault but what they are
getting at is that is this this weird
relationship between a culture's
uh individualism and the rise of tyranny
it's this weird thing how it works
together
if you have this individualist mindset
somehow we get more and more
collectivists and more and more
expansive in our government right it's
beautiful
well it i kind of i think it goes like
this i think it's really a
two or three step process uh you feel a
wrongness in the world
right and it's and it's and it's a it's
a felt sense right first and foremost
it's a false sense
second you can't fix it
you yourself and by you i mean yourself
and the
the real and the relationships that you
can count on
don't seem to be able to solve the
problem
now what do you do typically what we do
is we escape
one place you can get to is you can you
can deny the problem
you can make up a story that points the
blame at something
and renders you virtuous and those are
the two moves right the first move is
you find something which is vice
you point the blame at something the
second thing is you render yourself
virtuous
some volks escape into libertarianism
they point the point the blame at
authoritarianism or at
collectivism anything ends in ism and
renders themselves virtuous the
autonomous
you know individual some folks escape
into uh
social justice they point the blame it
fill in the blank
and always render themselves virtuous
that's that's the third move
right the first move is there is a felt
wrongness
second move is you feel powerless the
third move is you escape
now the problem is if you're sitting in
that third move and you're trying to
figure out how to solve things from the
third position
you're going to reinforce the second
position because the third position
can't solve anything
it only makes things worse and the worst
part is it makes things worse in a way
that actually creates
simple categories for other people to
start dividing and conquering
oh i'm a libertarian and the social
justice folks are clearly collectivists
so it's not just collectivists in
principle it's collectivists in practice
by the way they don't like me they
certainly they yell at me a lot they
point the finger they seem really mean
and angry and sometimes they even punch
me
so now i've got to read out reality
that's now that's the fourth move
there's a reality that is in fact really
real which increases the reality of the
wrongness but it's actually tied to the
third
which was never real in the first place
which is tied to the second which is
real real and all the way to the first
right so this you get real lost you get
confused and this is what's going on
right now
you can see it like surging through
social media you just sort of step back
and watch social media that lens
you keep seeing people who are
fundamentally
powerless fundamentally feel powerless
so they keep making up stories to try to
feel somewhat digentic
and then they mistake their stories for
reality and become actually powerless
so it's it's the site again it goes back
to
when you're in a stagnant universe at
least you feel that way
and you can't grow the pie the only
thing you have to do is to turn to your
neighbor and say well it's the choices
you've made
it's your race it's your gender it's
your ideology
which is causing the suffering in the
world you
need to be quarantined with all guilt
quarantined onto you
you need to quarantine all guilt onto
you and cut it off
that's that's the skateboard mechanism
it's still trying to happen it's nice
you know this put it in other places
right you could put it in this into the
stone on the ground
right i i think everybody's had that
experience as a child and stubbing your
toe on a stone
and blaming the stone first and foremost
so
let me think about that's a very nice
simple simple example i don't have to be
too high pollutant
right um i'm walking along and i stub my
toe in a stone what happens when i feel
pain and and the consequence the cause
is in the past
can't change it i'm in fact actually
powerless so i feel uncomfortable and
i'm actually powerless
so now i have a choice what do i do well
the energy the energy of of of
pain is an energy of change and i want
to change what happened but i can't
because it's in the past
so one of the things i might do is i
might blame something i can blame myself
that's uncomfortable i could also blame
the stone
it's funny you mentioned stick the stone
that's the metaphor for the uh
gospel transformation and the bible
scandal on the stumbling block that you
stumble onto in the field
and that's the that's the scandal that
that causes either
uh memetic rivalry because uh what's
when when peter
confronts jesus and he says uh you're
not gonna die on the cross we we're
gonna do
we're the one we're the 99 we're gonna
go beat the one percent okay it's time
to have the revolution jesus
you've got a movement here your poll
numbers are good let's storm the castle
uh and jesus says get behind me satan
which means get behind me accuser
you are a stumbling block to me so
you're a stone that i've stubbed my toe
on you're trying to draw me
into doing things the way of that
scarcity mindset
that's right that's right that's a real
i mean this is the silliest thing to say
that's a real insight yeah
yeah it's a real insight i think it's
it's a crucial land though right because
it's too easy
you can't help it right you kick the
stone um
there's a whole lot of instinct that
says well maybe what i should do is kick
you you stumble on stone maybe maybe i
should just kick the stone maybe the
stone got in the way
um and it's even harder because you have
to realize is that the first thing you
have to do
is you have to recognize that the pain
probably pulled you out of your
connection to the sacred
right you're you're you're now you've
been pulled back into the profane
and if you can build a a capacity now
we're
very simple again i stuff my toe my toe
hurts
the capacity to actually first and
foremost recognize what it feels like to
be pulled into the profane
and to slow down take a breath
look at your toe is it pain or is it
harm
if it's harm is it harm or is it is it
real damage
you know do i actually deal with
something if i do let's deal with
something
if it's just pain are there any things
that i could have done better
that i can use to change my capacity to
move forward in the world
if no then it's in the past it is simply
a part of reality that happens to occur
if yes then let's grow in that direction
as challenging as that may be
which having a two-year-old at home you
see that two-year-olds don't really have
too much of a trouble with it
and they stumble and fall they cry
because that's what happens
they allow the crime to pass through
without getting too hung up on blaming
anybody
then they figure out how to get better
and you know you just be
be like unto the child and learn how to
learn from your mistakes without blaming
anybody
it's probably a pretty good ancillary to
that particular rule yeah the kingdom of
god is like children that's what that's
what it's about
yeah that's the idea to be to be a child
to have that child-like lack of desire
to
scapegoat and tear down something else
um i think that's a picture
of what we're trying to describe yeah
you know and
it's funny because and i want to name it
we're having a conversation which has a
feeling of feeling a bit it's not
theoretical
but it's uh what's living in the in
the domain of language and and yet you
know i'm sitting in my
my chair using a computer to talk to you
over
telecommunications infrastructure and
you're a makeshift version of a boot
because we're quarantined right
voluntary
quarantine at least on my part i suppose
in some sense it's always voluntary and
that's important to recognize
right um
but things are things are afoot
normality is definitely
not going on outside i think i was it
yesterday where the pentagon had that
whole aliens thing and everybody looks
like and goes
you know it's going to take a lot more
than aliens to weird us out these days
um so i'd like to invite people to
accept the the reality of the signs
that the reality that you can actually
look around and go oh
this is that thing this is the telling
us that we're right now in the process
of making a real big choice
whether we spiral down into the
inevitable spiral of memetic desire into
conflict into chaos
into terror or we take this
this this stumbling block and we stumble
up
and we acknowledge oh that's right i
have to remember the difference between
the sacred and the profane
and i have to to return back to the path
before i do anything else and how do i
proceed forward in this space
more deeply in the sacred than i was
before and
find all those who would be friends you
know in the
in the uh quaker sense right the society
of friends the society of those who
agree to support each other
in maintaining their individual and
collective integrity in the shared space
of peace and grace in the sacred
and then build from there right because
that group that group of people
you know a group of people um who enter
into an agreement around that kind of a
shared
directionality is the only possible way
out of this mess
right right we're not going to get there
by pointing fingers we're not going to
get there by having
a boss tell us what to do i don't know
if you've noticed they're not very good
at it
uh and we're not going to get there by
blaming the boss either
that's the revolutionary counter spear
that imitates the spirit of the state
itself
both of them are the same thing and they
both lead to destruction revolutionary
overthrow
and the imposition of the old order they
they're they're almost they're identical
twins
that's identical twins look i'm a
christian so i'll continue to go back to
the gospel story
because it gives you all the tools you
need if you look at it you have the
story of the two jesus
you know there was two jesus's on trial
there with pilate
barabbas barabbas in the original text
his
in the earliest manuscripts he's named
jesus
they're all they took it out because
they thought some of those
uh scribes were saying this is a little
too close to home here this is a little
too edgy for us they took
they said how could the guy who's a a
profane
killer have the same name as the lord so
they they missed the point of the actual
gospel text
and they took the word jesus so there
was two a tale of two jesus's
in the story of pilate you have jesus
bar means of abba of the father so you
have two
yeshua of the father two jesus of the
father
so the question the crowd has to choose
is which jesus do you want do you want
the jesus who's
because remember that barabbas was not
just a serial killer he wasn't jack the
ripper
he was a he was a revolutionary he was
like william wallace
he the word they used was a
revolutionary overthrower so he
he was the jesus that peter wanted jesus
to be
remember peter was like wait a second
you're not going to die on the cross
you're not letting up your power you're
not letting go of power
you're not doing that we have a thing
here we can have we can have justice
we're going to take you into the throne
you're going to be the the president
you're going to be the key
um but there's a jesus there that offers
that that's jesus barabbas
and pilate says which guy do you want to
let free and which guy do you want to
kill
and the crowd chooses the jesus who
tried to overthrow things like william
wallace did
and they chose to kill and butcher the
jesus who said
uh oh jerusalem oh jerusalem if you had
only known the ways of peace
but they've been hidden from your eyes
now i think here's my
thing i think the one danger and i've
told this to jordan peterson in my
interview with him is that
we cannot keep the story of jesus in the
domain of the mythic poetic
i don't think it's just another
archetypal story
and i think if we don't see that that
we will miss how different it is from
the dying and rising savior myths of
our mythological past ah nice does that
make sense
so if you if you don't if you think of
jesus as just um
learning abstract ideas like uh
oh uh clean up my room okay that's fine
but
if you don't actually see it as a
tangible human person
you can actually imitate a real
historical person
then you don't have any basis i think to
actually try to do this contagious
positive mimesis of
you need a concrete real human person to
imitate
and so what we've done is we're so we're
so christian we don't realize it that we
don't want to acknowledge the
the uh the the the concrete reality
of how the story of jesus's life has
transformed the world we're so christian
that we feel the need to defer
to those other religions oh you know i
you know remember what he said if you
want to be
the greatest among you you've got to be
a servant so we we have that servant's
posture for all other
uh religious ideas they're all one
mythological group you see what i mean
we get that idea because of how
thoroughly christian
we are does that make sense we've all
we've turned this into one mythological
ethereal group of archetypes
but we we make that mistake for a few
reasons one because we're more
christianized than we want to
recognize we're more uh
if you want to be first you have to be
the least of these you have to serve you
have to
wash the feet of your of yours of those
below you
and so we say well we self-flagellate we
self-flagellate
the religious inheritance that has built
the west
oh it's no it's no different it's no
distinct it's not it's not superior to
any other ideas it's but every other you
know that's that's a unique con that's a
unique attribute of the west
this desire to um
to self to self criticize to self
graduate does that make sense it occurs
to me that there's actually a very
simple solution to this
um how do i say it
uh what is it and the truth shall set
you free i think that that seems like
that's the answer which is
what i mean by that is this um
if need be and with john jonathan pagio
i will agree that it is
ideal if it not need be but if need be i
can simply wake up tomorrow morning anew
with no memory of any stories that
anybody's told whatsoever
i don't need to i don't necessarily need
to have the mythopoetics of any
story including the jesus story because
it's just
truth so all i do is pay attention to
what is in fact really true
and to what reality is telling me i will
recover those stories
where they are most true now this will
be a very challenging thing to
accomplish right and i'll be very
unlikely to accomplish that
in practice because the world is vast
and i am small but nonetheless if you
use that as your as your compass
and you say oh well we've been given a
uh an orienting basis
we've been given um a way to make our
job a lot simpler
you know how to find our way onto the
path and and and um
a bunch of parables that gives us some
clarity on what kinds of things work
what kinds of things don't work right
but it's about a practice and it's about
a actual
i think in fact we're saying it's just
the thing that you're supposed to be
doing is actually
learning how to live it better and
better and learning how to
embody it right but you can't but but
the difference is there is a distinction
between
zeus and jesus as a role model sure
but you don't necessarily the dying
rising god of
horus is different from jesus does that
make sense because horus
he's repeating the same cycle of the
profane
of the pro of trying to maintain uh
order through the sacrifice of one what
jesus story does
he doesn't create unity with his
resurrection he creates division
all other reported resurrections in
history that humans believed in
created unity his creates division
because in his you know um
all mythological stories that gerard
points to
this is why he became a christian he saw
he saw what he believed in a physical
resurrection of jesus
once he understood that it was the
revelation of the concealment of that
eternal
return you know that nietzsche talks
about
risha understood it too by the way
nietzsche understood what
was so special about the jesus story
that he was terrified of
he was terrified because he unders he
believed that it had destroyed the
sacred it had destroyed the order
of the universe that had kept things in
place the hierarchy
the unity the peace it had destroyed it
and he was afraid he was afraid that not
enough people could ever
fully imitate jesus to ever save us from
what it had done that
jesus story had blown things up but
human beings
were incapable of actually imitating him
to the point where
it would bring a new order in the way
jesus envisioned you see
this this is the story of the last men
like which is where we were so much
so so far we are right now right so in
in in nietzsche's
niche's vision as i'm i'm bouncing it
off of you
there's a move where the
the order that we were talking about
earlier the order that was created by
the profaned violence holding back the
profane violence
right was in fact destroyed and um
as that that's what jesus yeah exactly
just to hold you're right it's profane
violence holding back profane violence
that we used to think was sacred we
thought it was sacred
jesus says it's all profane yep if you
kill one for the
because that the whole story with
pontius pilate it's better that one man
died for the whole
than the whole nation perish that's his
statement not excuse me that's not
pontius that's caiaphas caiaphas says
that
he says it's better that one man died
than the whole nation perish
and that's the that's his logic for
murdering jesus
and so the story that's your that's the
breaking of the fourth wall for the text
right there
as it's breaking the fourth wall all the
way through but it's really close right
there that you see it
it's not better that one man died for
the whole nation that the whole nation
should not perish that's
that's the whole story of jesus story
yes yes right if you think about it
going back to our earliest metaphor of
scarcity
right the the mentality of
well that guy's going to have to starve
to death because we haven't got enough
fish to go around
right that's that mentality right it's
better that one man died in the whole
nation parish it's better that we agree
that that particular individual like
look it's we haven't gotten a fish to go
around people
we're gonna have to agree one of us is
gonna have to die but we have to make
that choice to save the rest of us
it's better that we put a drug dealer
into a rape cage called prison than the
whole nation perish if they're addicted
to the drug it's better that one tax
evader
gets thrown into a rape cage than the
whole nation perish if we don't have a
tax system based by force
it's better that everything on the blast
yeah yeah the whole system
that's the slope you're on that slippery
slope and you can uh
and that's where we're in that's that's
the system that we're still bound up in
that we're trying to free ourselves from
yes i i i concur with that assessment
and then the other side of it
is then the challenge the burden
the burden is upon everyone to choose to
endeavor to live in the
in the fashion that jesus describes
and to actually accomplish that goal
right with enough of us
so that we can actually live on the
other side of that transition the other
side of the eye of the needle right but
it's not
simba it's not luke skywalker
i want people to see that simba and and
lion king and star wars those are
christianized but they're still
completely pagan pagan myths because it
always resolves with
the murder of the enemy with jesus it's
the opposite
yeah we don't like to tell that story
well it's interesting too
wow so let's try this on for size i'm
not sure if this is right but there's
some
it just popped into my head um i've been
talking to john vervice if i'm talking
to him again later today
and part of that conversation has been
about the um
the salience of the dramatic story
you know the story of of luke skywalker
killing the the bad guy and becoming the
new noble king
sells people like that's a sexy story
um oh wow how's that work
and technically he doesn't kill the bad
guy to be fair his father
kills the bad guy he actually redeems he
redeems
his father who kills the bad guy but
nonetheless but there's still a killing
there's still a sacrifice there's still
a witch that had to be burned and that
was emperor
what jesus does is jesus says look at
emperor palpatine he needs to be loved
he needs to be brought into the camp
emperor palpatine only looks like that
because he has leprosy and he had a bad
childhood
that's what jesus does nobody watches
that movie
nobody watches that movie that's the key
we
i've talked a lot well it's funny
i've talked a lot with the people who i
talk with very closely
i don't think i've even said this out
loud but this one of the things that my
heart
has definitely told me many times is
that we we need to move into a
post-narrative
world which is merely to say a
post-drama world
you know a world where we acknowledge
the reality that
peace may not be as uh salient
it's not as potent a drug as drama
and it's the simplest thing you know uh
if you take a look at i remember
watching teenagers talk about this in
the context of
of television when cell phones started
showing up
and you know the classic uh drama in a
in a social interpersonal drama
is the drama of confusion person a
thinks person b did
or thinks x and so they go off into some
kind of dramatic conflict
and of course the teenagers are going
why don't you just call them well let's
just act like mature grown-ups and just
have a conversation about
the miscommunication maybe the hurt
feelings or the fear
that you have about what's going on if
you can actually maturity
dissolves drama and it's interesting how
addicted we are
to drama because drama sells drama is a
story that likes to be told drama is
repeated we gossip drama
we very rarely gossip um healthy
stories of of maturity um
solving problems in a simple and rich
and sustainable way so that's another
addiction we're gonna have to figure out
how to shake
well that's why that's why even the
church has reinserted pagan elements of
god's character back into its own story
because it yeah
it's hard to sell a god that has
no scarcity in his love he has
unconditional love that doesn't sell for
human beings
we like gods that are made in our image
that give tit for tat that give push
pull that give
what we call seduction i love you but i
might kill you
i love you but i might blow your whole
village up well
you're not competing for a bargain right
we're like a guy who cuts deals
and what jesus says is he's forgiving
his enemies while they're murdering him
he doesn't say i'll forgive them if you
if you uh if they get me off this cross
yeah okay so this is good here's here's
a shift and i think this
tried this shift because i've struggled
with this a lot and i think i've found a
comfort with it which is um at least i
can do this right ah okay
so remember that that structure i gave
earlier about
first wrongness all around down to
fourth okay
now if you're sitting there in the pits
of fourth and somebody comes to you and
says the phrase
unconditional love quite often the way
that you imagine that
is kind of like unlimited money
you think of it as oh i can do anything
and still have
approval something like that you don't
actually know what love even vaguely
means and therefore
unconditional love you haven't got a
clue what it actually means
now if you think about it in the context
of just good parenting so every parent
should give their child unconditional
love i'm going to say that absolutely
categorically
right there if there's anything in the
world that i believe with experience it
is that
now that does not mean that every parent
should indulge their child by giving
them their
uh approval certainly doesn't mean that
every parent should give their child
unconditional candy
right right candy and love are not the
same thing right there's still
boundaries right unconditional love is a
crucible more than it is anything else
right unconditional love is that i make
a commitment
to so fully love you that i
seek in all ways through that love to
support you
in becoming the highest version of
yourself and i am in partnership with
your soul
and your soul is not kind now your soul
knows that to grow you have to go
through
there's an undergoing in growth and to
unconditional love is to be
fully in relationship with your soul's
calling
for you to grow into becoming who it is
you are to become on this earth
which may actually have a great deal of
suffering involved right
if i see a man on the street i actually
remember this and i'll um
sort of out myself a little bit i was in
i was in an ayahuasca ceremony
and um the the question the in crew that
i put to myself was the question of what
is what is mine to do
and as it turns out in in the ceremony
there was a young man
probably in his early 20s who had been
able to get his father
his grandmother and his aunt but not his
mother i don't know what happened there
to join them and they were they were
definitely not the kind of folks you'd
expect to be in this kind of a scenario
and dad was sitting next to me and dad
had a very tough time
my dad was undergoing some serious
suffering probably under and
i think he may have been a vietnam
veteran so he's going to some
world-class
suffering and part of me wanted to reach
out to him
and i was feeling his suffering and i
was feeling a oh my gosh
and then all of a sudden it just came
clear to me of oh this is my lesson
my lesson is to actually love him
unconditionally which does not mean to
carry his cross for him
quite the opposite is to actually figure
out with as much discernment as i can
muster which may
not be much right now um
precisely what his mind to do in
relationship to him and precisely what
it is to do in relationship to himself
and there are that's parenting again
right parenting as a child
now your job as a parent is not to lift
your child's burden and your
job is not to put on your child of
burdens nonsense to carry
is to support them in growing in their
own capacity to discover for themselves
to build in themselves in increasing
capacity to notice
what is theirs to do and how to actually
hold the cross that is theirs to hold
for the whole and for themselves to grow
into who it is there they become
it is an infinitely challenging task and
you will always get it wrong
that is it though that's the whole story
that's the beginning of the end and i
would just call that friendship by the
way once you recognize that every
relationship is that relationship
and every relationship where you either
try to lift or to impose a burden into
somebody else's
is a sin is an error of the of the most
grievous sort
and that your own your own journey is a
journey that gives you more capacity to
learn
how to under how to discern that then i
just start to get to deep
well that's what peter was trying to do
with jesus he's like don't die at a
cross
i'll stop you i'll save you i'll protect
you and he's like you don't know what
you're talking about
you know you're still operating come on
but that's the thing peter i got bad
news for you um
you're actually trying to do is you're
actually trying to put down your own
burden
which is to the burden of witnessing me
on the cross
right right he's mindful the fact you're
actually trying to avoid your own cross
by by pretending to carry mine right
it's not until
it's not until they reportedly see a
resurrection
with jesus that they actually understand
what he was doing all along
up until that point they were bound up
in the crowd too
and abandoned him in his moment of
persecution
it wasn't until they saw the empty tomb
and physically went to their deaths
and it was also interesting that they
used you know women were reported to be
the first witnesses so if they wanted to
make up a myth
why would you put women at the time when
they would be considered not even worth
uh any kind of credible testimony in the
court of law
so if they're trying to make if they're
trying to sell you on a lie
they wouldn't put women as the first uh
witnesses to the resurrected christ they
would they would
because they know that would be worth
like a child or
in terms of court testimony so they see
something they really truly believe
and it transforms everything that they
saw to the point where they leave
all their embarrassing moments in the
gospels that they miss it
over and over and over again it's a very
repented it's a very uh
uh transformed text because
they're they're the villains in the
whole story the guys that
are the leaders who preserve these
gospel stories
they're getting it wrong over and over
and over who will rule
who will rule when your kingdom no guys
it's not going to be like that
you know hey jesus you're walking on
water we're scared
we're going to stay bowing in this boat
he's like no guys get up and do it like
me
walk on on h2o with me
then i mean be me and then he tries to
spell it out for us but we still get it
because it says
eat my body drink my blood i mean how
much more visceral
can you get to the idea of imitation
than that
right because he's he's calling into
when he does that
he's calling us back to our unknown
origins that we
we created order we created language the
first symbol
i agree with gerard that the first
symbol
is the sacrificial victim cannibalized
cannibalized
for the propitiation of the community
for the atonement
for the coming together of the the
stress of scarcity
and death anxiety and all that stuff you
come together
and you eat the body you drink the blood
of a common victim that's the origins of
human civilization
so jesus is intentionally calling that
into play i believe
when he says eat my body drink my blood
meaning
if you want to take out your pain and
suffering blame me
if you want to take out somebody make me
your punching bag
if you were raised in a church that you
felt was oppressive
blame jesus you know take it out on me i
can take it don't take it out on each
other
if you need a scapegoat scapegoat me
eat me don't eat each other you eat each
other every time you try to lord over
each other in your business
cut cutthroat practices that exploit
people
or desire you're eating each other
constantly it's all based in cannibalism
and that's the whole reason why the
church is called to eat
and drink in remembrance of the body
that was torn up
that was torn apart right you're you're
recalling the origins of the human
species every time you partake of the
eucharist
and you're recalling it in a satirical
yeah
but you're but that's the thing it's the
joke's on you if you don't get it
because what happens is
we we we end up actually uh
to to to really participate in the lit
in the eucharist is to renounce
and to acknowledge that all of our ways
of being are founded on that hidden
moment of cannibalism
that we think we're fake we're way past
does that make sense
it's a satire when you partake in the
eucharist it's a satire in human beings
it's it's a performative art that you do
it's performance art
you're satirizing the the pomp and
circumstance and the decorum
and the grandeur of human civilization
because you're recognizing that
underneath it all is a corpse that we
partake of together
yeah i'm just i'm just reflecting on
this this this narrative of the
of the injection of salinas the
injection of
drama the injection of uh formalism the
injection of pomp and circumstance and
lights and
fanciness right special effects putting
special effects on the story
that has the advantage of getting a uh
you know a farmer
to give you his attention for a little
bit has the disadvantage
of missing the whole point um
which is neither here nor there i mean i
certainly haven't done a particularly
good job of conveying anything of any
mean means it's uh
to the degree to which the church has
been able to do anything at all for
thousands of years
that's miraculous in and of itself but
going back to where we are um
i i mean i've said it out loud so i'll
say it out loud here
i really do believe that we're getting
pretty close to the point where we're
gonna have to actually figure this have
to figure this out for real
um you know if it's not in this
particular crisis and i've called it a
meta crisis just to kind of give it
context right metacrisis is
revealing the fragility the fact
that the profane violence holding back
profane violence is
barely holding holding it back
if it's not this particular perturbation
there's another one coming and another
one and they're going to get bigger and
they're going to get faster
until either the thing breaks and we
find ourselves tumbling down
or we figure out how to go through the
eye of the needle or
you know something along those lines and
it's not going to be long
and i don't mean that in terms of
i wasn't i was not raised in any
meaningful sense of christian so
i don't mean that in a revelation sense
i mean that in a very practical sense of
you know when i take a look at economics
and i take a look at geopolitics and
take a look at
flows of of molecules of energy i think
look at innovation i take a look at
mimetics right i take a look at physical
phenomena happening in the world and i
understand things like
catastrophe theory which is a branch of
mathematics and understand
self-organizing criticality i understand
complex system science i understand
fragility right i understand all these
things
what i do is i say there's a storm of
bruin
it's a thunderstorm there's going to be
a lightning bolt and it's going to
happen in the next 24 hours right i can
do meteorology on this thing
and i'm saying we're coming pretty close
um we haven't got a whole lot of time
and so this is a
for me it's a very practical exercise
i'm not in the least bit
kidding when i when i say what i'm
saying at least in terms of my own life
and how we pull that off well
let's hope that it's uh how do i say
this
let us let us hope that the miracle of
the loaves and the fishes
is is closer to hand than perhaps we
believe it is
i think the way we one of the steps that
gets us there
is recognizing that the knowledge
and it's happening but that the the
calcified
enshrined bodies of knowledge that we
believe to be
sacrosanct are actually
mythically enclosed more than we believe
and then once we begin to think about
that and it's scary
because this is where you'll realize how
much social pressure
is actually built into what we call
knowledge in science
and that the sooner we start to have the
courage to speak out about these things
and think
critically about what is nature and i
would say you know people dismiss the
idea and
i'm just using this as an example they
dismiss the idea of course jesus is a
story
and i would say yes the most important
thing is to imitate the character of
jesus
uh and not quibble about some of the the
fights about dogma but i would also say
that um you know people would say you
know that of course
there's no such thing as a physical
resurrection that defies nature and i
would say well
how do you know what nature is if you
don't know what nature is how would you
know what super nature is
above nature if you don't even know what
real nature really is
then how can you even begin to give us a
credible
uh critique of oh no this is outside of
nature
because i know what nature is that's
outside of nature therefore it's
supernatural
it's a myth it's fake never happened now
i would say
that one of the things that's going to
help us break through to the other side
is as a species is to recognize that
our our settled science for so many
things including things as simple as the
atom
are so much in the dark we have no idea
and we have to have the humility the
epistemological humility
and the courage most importantly because
we're afraid to say
we're afraid to call out icons of
knowledge
of who what's the atom what is nuclear
energy what are i'm just taking that
example
that we're afraid to question that
because we don't want to be socially
ashamed as
alternative physics or pseudoscience or
quack you're so scared of the memetic
social pressure
that builds up these institutions we
think they're science
we don't understand how religiously
structured they actually are thomas kuhn
gave us a little clue
with the idea about faith being the
edifice for
reigning dog you know reigning
scientific paradigms
but i think if you take gerard and you
take thomas coon
you might have a better picture at how
much we need to re-question things that
we think are settled science does that
make sense
of course i i could not agree more
strongly i think it's um
and again i i like the false dichotomy
put out there there's a
and it's very similar to the one we were
talking about earlier like we created
sort of a false distinction between
authoritarians and libertarians
and that recognized recognizes that
false distinction is what causes both of
those to begin to show up they co-create
each other and could not exist without
each other
um same thing happens here right your
your
sort of scientific authoritarian has to
categorize critical thinking as
pseudoscience but that does not mean
there isn't such a thing as
pseudoscience right of course
there is magical thinking in this and
it's out there too and unfortunately
magical thinking has to
categorize um
magical thinking has to identify rigor
as authoritarian and you get an error
and you get trapped you can't actually
be in that place in the middle
where you're trying to be humble
humility right neither position has a
lot of humility
both positions very righteous about
their rightness
um but if you have a place of humility
around reality then you're
in a place of being able to say i'm
alright i mean if if push comes to shove
and most of the times it doesn't i'm
going to assume a whole bunch of things
about the nature of reality
um but generally speaking my job is to
create as much space as possible
to be as open as possible as reality
could give me because that's how you do
things that's how you learn new things
right
um so yes and by the way you can also
work it backwards
as it turns out you can actually take a
look at the
scientific revolutions and start to see
when they occur and how they occur and
what their characteristics and
trajectories look like
and say oh we're actually kind of due
for one we've been sort of sitting
sitting spinning in a an increasingly
landlocked
uh um miasma
of stuff not moving around for a while
and this is usually a sign
that a break is about to occur
so what does that mean well it's hard to
know it's very hard to know
i certainly agree with nietzsche's point
that we do not yet know what the body
can do which is just another way of
saying let us be
humble in the face of what is real
how can you um
advance the world of atoms if you don't
really know what an atom really is
that's the way i think about it that'll
definitely slow you down won't it
but but to have but to have the courage
to even speak about it publicly i mean
even the most radical
innovative brands that we can think of
we're still trained we don't realize how
mimetically
enclosed we are to we're afraid to say
well i don't agree that monocharged
particles exist
when they say well who are you have you
are you one of the established priests
who are you
what school did you go to to be
catechized
how many papers from our established
class of folks with billions of
government and political dollars
protecting our established class
who are you and have you ever had one of
your papers
come close to meeting our tree house
you know it's a tree house you know
you're not in the tree house do you know
the code
and so everybody says well i want to be
a respectable person i need to make
money
i've got a career to go i'm not going to
question anything i'm just going to
sit down and shut up and hope
that somewhere down the road someone
will have the credentials
to challenge like martin luther the
church
of science ah see what i mean it takes
someone from the inside
usually if you know martin luther was a
a monks monk
and you had to have a monk's monk come
in there and say hey
i'm an insider this is all bs a
whistleblower well sure enough because i
mean this must be very clear
uh physics is a real thing there's a lot
of they can do a lot of stuff
they can make transistors they can make
laser beams right you can do real stuff
and it's hard
and there's a lot of work put into it
i don't understand it deeply enough to
like exercise a true critique of physics
ptolemaic uh views of the world were
very good at charting uh
ship courses yep there's there's and if
you didn't know it from the inside well
enough you were going to have real
trouble so you need one of two things
right
you either need somebody who's on you
need martin luther
to come and say hey guys i needed to
sort of share with the hoi polloi what
all of us kind of know which is
the emperor has a lot less clothes than
emperor likes to pretend
um which maybe is the kind of thing that
eric's been about
or you need to actually do something
which is truly powerful and new
it doesn't require you to get permission
from the church that's right that's it
that's the thing that's what that's what
has to happen you have to
i know this is going to sound weird but
you know it's like the the miracle of
the fishes and lows you've got to do
demonstrations
so let me give you let me give you my
mind there so um
that's the way science used to be done
by the way tesla would do a
demonstration in the public you didn't
have to have like beer he's like look at
this
this is actually imagine if he had to go
through the peer
peer journals to get his stuff out
nothing you know we'd still be using
what dc current
fry in our heads check this out i think
this is going to be great i think
this is going to be a really nice uh
piece particularly for everybody who
or anybody i don't know if ever anybody
ever listens to these things says the
two of us and as far as i'm concerned
that's okay because this has been a good
conversation from my point of view
um all right so if i was going to try to
really chip away
at this the pseudo-sacred edifice of
science
i definitely wouldn't go after physics i
wouldn't go after biology neither why is
that the holy of holies
it's the holy of holies and it's it's
protected by a lot of veils right i
don't understand exactly how to do all
the stuff there i'm
you know i i dropped out of high s yeah
you go behind that veil you'll see a lot
of mirrors man
little funny house of mirrors where am i
looking yeah
and i can i can like i can i can tell
when somebody's um
trying to bamboozle me but at the same
time i've you know i've spent a lot of
time some
i i i don't know murray gal man is a
guy who created a big piece of the
standard model i've met murray
very smart guy and working real hard to
try to tell the truth
so i'm not casting any disper aspersions
in physics but we can go after the holy
holies
largely because it's strong right it's
you know solid edifice and it's done
real stuff they build nuclear bombs and
lasers man
it's hard to impeach i wouldn't
necessarily go after
after chemistry or biology i'd go after
economics
because one those don't know
what the hell they're talking about
they're full of straight up and
down
two they like to pretend like they're
doing science right they put on the
whole vest the robes of science and they
put on the hats and they carry the
scepters and they
sort of stomp around and say nah we're
physicists um
and therefore control all kinds of stuff
like this
like the asymmetry physicists
have pretty solid stuff and create real
things like laser beams and nuclear
bombs
um and that don't actually have that
much influence
in how the world works in terms of what
they say economists they don't have much
influence
not really like you know richard feynman
i would say it's
i think it would be in the background
though they're they're they are so
rarified that their influence doesn't
have to be manifestly made
yeah they have a very very deep
influence around the holy of holies
i think that's right yeah i think i i
have just to hope just to
just to add to that i think that that's
because i call it the mowgli effect the
jungle book effect
whoever discovers the fire is the one
who who's the king of the jungle
you know and so whoever creates the fire
of nuclear bombs that can
blow the whole world up automatically
gets the keys to the kingdom as the hot
the highest
most rarefied knowledge so you go
through they they will not be questioned
because they have
fire so my point is i wouldn't i
wouldn't um
for the for everybody who's not in the
center of the holy of holies
it's very difficult to and i would say
even
potentially impossible to go after
physics
um and you can't speak to it at a
personal experience very well
but economics you sure can right
economics the
the the the science is not even vague
this science
the empirical evidence is 150 180
the opposite direction i remember in
2008 sitting there and watching people
like paul krugman writing down what he
said and checking it a few days later
and saying that was wrong
completely that was wrong completely all
right so these guys have a really cool
habit of saying things out loud that are
absolutely impeachable
uh historically empirically um
and and yet right and yet they are
inside
the temple and they sit next to and play
play roles with as if they are also
doing science if i wanted to unravel
that sweater
i go right there if you start unraveling
the sweater lots of things start to
change and then you'll find yourself eye
to eye because remember what holds the
physicists in charge
is as you said the end of the day it's
budgets
at the end of the day it's it's it's the
ability to say you know young kid who's
getting a phd
you're thinking real interesting
thoughts if you'd like to get to
to be a professor and get paid to do
physics probably ought to think slightly
different
interesting thoughts right but if they
didn't have that ability if anybody
could think what they wanted to think
and not have to
kowtow to those guys then their power
would go away really quickly because
then reality would reestablish itself
well also if the state wasn't i mean
this is another
an economic way to look at it if the
state wasn't funding science we'd find
out the truth of the physics and
chemistry and
a lot of things a lot faster because
money would have would be allocated
towards solutions that actually work and
produce real results that's why science
used to
yeah that's where i'd go right i'd go
after i mean where does
science meet reality at economics
because economics touches on the market
but
so so you're saying if you were going
into the temple you'd go after the money
changers before you opened the veil
right
i would go after the money changes
that's exactly what i would do and right
after he went after the money changers
eventually
the veil was ripped and there was no one
home in the holy of holies you see
is that right yeah yeah but that's the
stuff he does the money changer thing he
goes after the economics guys
that gets him killed and as he's killed
it says the veil is torn and there was
no one home you know oh wow
there's nobody there i i reckon we ought
to go after the money changers first
so how do we go after the money changes
do you have i mean i i'm going to give
you my
i like austrian economics do you don't
like that i'm sure you're
i'm very well i'm very familiar with
austrian economics and i would say by
and large i feel good about it
the problem i got with austrian
economics is that it um
it uh what do you call it fetishized it
worships that golden calf
quite specifically and i think that
that's uh not quite as
as accurate as it should be but i
definitely take a solid but wouldn't the
true austrians just say
money should be up to the market so if
they want to use uh wampum or seashells
they can if they want to use bitcoin
they can just i guess that's
the no true scotsman argument to be fair
i i do not position myself as being
among the uh the theology of
austrian economics i cannot tell you
what a true austrian would say right
right
most of the folks i know who who present
themselves of that lineage
they like gold yeah yeah so that so
you're saying we need something new
to to storm the castle of economics or
is that what you're suggesting
yeah i think we do what does that look
like is there something being developed
in that vein or you're just saying it's
something we need to do
it hasn't been done yet um i think a lot
of things frankly have been developed i
mean
ever since ever since our friends at
bitcoin cracked open the code of saying
hey why don't we think about money
why don't we actually just contemplate
that as a sort of thing that we don't
just
you know prior to bitcoin money was
either the government
makes it magical and we kind of don't
think about it too hard or
you know a small group of guys with dust
on them said no it's gold and that's
pretty much it right
after bitcoin a whole bunch of people
are like well i'm just going to kind of
think about it
my sense is we can hit that
we can hit money and my guess is that it
actually ain't that hard to be honest
because we can i'll give you an example
one of the things i actually did a video
on universal basic income you could take
a look at it
i said the way i look at it i think
about it not from the point of view of
trying to use the metaphors that have
been produced by the economics
profession because i'm going to be right
out front i think the economic
profession
up until maybe like i like the the old
guys like the real old guys the guys who
were doing their stuff in the
in the 1900s and the early 20th
centuries i think they were earnestly
biologists in the botanist sense like
they're collecting like natural
scientists
it's when you get to the the more
current generations that i get
real skeptical um
but i think about it sort of the market
as supposed to be collective
intelligence right that's what it's
supposed to be
the market is a way to have everybody
benefit from the perspective
and the insight and the intelligence the
actual capacity to separate
reality from from illusion of everybody
else and it's a tool to do that
and uh well so the brain is also a form
of collective intelligence and so is a
network
okay cool let's try to look at neurology
neuroscience let's look at graph theory
network theory and let's look at markets
and see if there's something we can
learn by taking all three of those
disciplines and stick them together into
a single transdisciplinary container
and my answer is for more or less yes in
fact we can we can get some really
really good ideas out of that we can do
a restructuring of how
the collective intelligence of the
market operates
to create something which does the thing
the market is supposed to do
um well like actually do the thing but
it was promised
um i just recognized there's some some
insights into how
network topologies like use evolution
the brain is evolution
trying to figure out how to get a whole
bunch of neurons and perceptors and
actuators
to coordinate into a highly effective
decentralized mechanism
okay great let's do some biomimicry and
see what does that tell us about how
markets maybe ought to operate
um and then of course network theory
gives us the ability to actually do
real-time simulations of that same
underlying set of questions and
understand a whole bunch of things using
a variety of actual
like either a how our networks have
actually evolved which we can see now
but it gives us data we can actually see
it with precision
and then b we can actually run
simulations on it so
those two vectors if you if you kind of
double click on that and say let's let's
rethink these concepts
not not have a uh not fetishize
economics in the way that physicists
have been fetishizing physics let's just
be
aware of the fact that a lot of the
things that we may think are true are
probably
not probably in many cases may be less
true than we think they are
or we hold them too close and start
looking at it
i think we can do some really good work
fast i don't think it would take us very
long because
let me pause on that for a minute one
more sort of piece of theory that i
think is pretty important
because we go back we talked about this
in terms of peter's proposition peter
thiel's proposition
and my proposition and i think many
other people that something happened in
the 70s things went awful sideways
one of the theories to which i ascribe
meaningfully
is um
a schumpeter i think our french
trumpeter actually
hit the nail on the head pretty well
creative destruction in fact
specifically s-curves
and um my sense is that around about the
mid-70s we were beginning the process at
the end
of that era and that we should have been
moving into a truly new era
but unfortunately there were powers that
be they had the capacity
to prevent that from happening so
instead of truly moving into an actual
new era
in the 80s and 90s which is when we
should have been in the childhood of
that era
we went through the great moderation
which also ended up as the great
financialization
and that constrained we still got some
stuff out of the new era right we got
computers
but computers ended up being an artifact
that was independent to the existing
structure
maximally minimum disruption maximum
appendage
and was mostly financialized so you've
got something like microsoft which is
this grotesque capture
of the energy of what should have
happened and turns most of it into
most of it into money and most of it
into minimum disruption
for example just as as one piece of it
the reason why i'm bringing that up is
we should right now be sitting in a
mature
next thing right school should have
changed
banking should have changed governance
should have changed a lot right at least
as much as what happened between
1914 and 1945 right that period of
transition between the victorian era
and the modern era a lot changed that
same amount should have changed between
1972 and say
1999 somewhere why didn't well
we could talk about it in detail if we'd
like but i'm just going to say that
the capacity of the institutions of
control
to control the profane power that was
holding back profane violence
was able to prevent the disruption that
would have violated its own
capacity to be in power right
the combination of removing the capacity
to connect with reality through money
the ability to remove the capacity
connected to reality through narrative
both narrative addicting generations
on fantasy through television the
ability to manipulate those generations
through the power of propaganda and
television
putting every child through industrial
education which narrows the mind and
and turns it into an optimizing
effectiveness machine
i i think it also biases the left brain
hemisphere as
is the left brain hemisphere ian mcgill
chris i did an interview with him
recently and we talked about that our
institutions of knowledge or left brain
hemisphere are biased you know very
powerful
very powerful because the light the
right brain if you listen to it all has
been going
for a long time i thought it was more
like
um
[Laughter]
[Music]
and so anyway end up getting is also in
the economy i think about what happened
when they said okay we're going to take
all the folks who are able to tap into
that right brand let's take jim morrison
and let's turn him into a celebrity
which makes money and has
celebrity status and then let's turn
that into a market
and here i'm using the word market in
the negative sense right not the
positive sense which is to say
that which to the profane let's turn the
sacred into profane let's turn that
that thing which is here to liberate us
and let's turn into something which
actually traps us even more deeply
and then and then also demoralizes us
around the sacred in general so we can't
even connect with that channel any
longer
and every version that channel in the
future starts looking a lot more like
jon bon juvie and less and less like uh
uh jim morrison i'm dating myself pick
your favorite
version of the sort of uh high salient
slow
road relevance rockstar madonna even
better
um lady gaga perhaps so
so that's the piece right so there are
techniques and capacities for for
control
across all dimensions of society they
had a vested interest in maintaining
that control
and capacity to do so sadly enough at
least adequately to hold
in evolution is called niche
construction so the dams were built and
the dams the levees held back
the river in spite of the river's desire
to shift its banks
so we should be sitting in a mature
other place and we should actually have
developed a lot of capacity and
competence we actually should be a very
different people right now
nonetheless a lot of that work was
actually done
a lot of that work was developed by
strange weird folks who were living in
corners all over the place and thinking
thoughts and trying to figure things out
on their own
sometimes just unable to play in the
game that was set before them
and again i can just invoke my friend
eric and brett as examples of that so
there was
that those folks are hanging out in the
wilderness where the scapegoats are
there that's right that's right hanging
out in the wilderness with the
scapegoats around quite often being
scapegoats on
not rare occasions and most of the time
being broken and destroyed and
rendered incapable and voiceless but
a lot of work was done in that period of
time a lot of work has been done so
it's not so much i think our job is to
invent from scratch
i think a lot of our job is to actually
rediscover and to synthesize and to
integrate and to redeem
and to bring back into right
relationship and to
and to recover that's just an easier job
it's very good very good because what
you're saying there is very it's
interesting to me because
i'm going to use that story of of
the the christ story again just to kind
of give you a picture of what i think
you're getting at here
there's these scapegoats out in the
wilderness right
and they have these knowledge projects
that they're working on
and our job is to bear witness
and bring that scapegoat back into
community
in the same way as this what happened i
always call the gospels the gospel
technology
because what it is is it's a piece of
media
written from the vantage point of the
scapegoat rather than the winning crowd
up into that point all myths had been
written from the vantage point of the
winning crowd
and to this day we believe in something
called the edible complex
that oedipus actually killed his dad and
had sex with his mother
we still scapegoat him by our own
psychological inheritance of our
modernistic
uh uh science so so what i'm saying is
all history had been written for the
winner's crowd
and then the gospels are a piece of
media that say actually no
if you take the camera and play the same
action
sequence but give the camera to the
scapegoat you'll see a whole new
universe and what i think happens here
this is why i call the technology is
if we imitate the gospel writers and
take the camera of history
and give it to the scapegoats who've
been banished to the hinterlands
then we'll see the same sequence of
events of what is economics what is
physics
what is all this stuff nutrition and
we'll see it play out from a different
angle
and it will allow people to
make progress and move ahead as a
species
so so this goes back to the wonderful
point which is
media technology back to mcluhan we're
back to mcclure
media technology is what allows us to
imitate the gospel technology of handing
the cameras
to the banished scapegoats who have been
banished from the institutional spheres
of
biology and so on and psychology and
anthropology gerard was banished from
anthropology and still is
to some degree and uh economics and
physics
and we hand those camera views it
doesn't mean all scapegoats are right
right because when you're out there
because some people are scapegoated
because they're
they're wrong or they're well annoyed
let's be very honest
there's a whole bunch here so what i
would say is that the part of that we've
done that we've done the first part
the first part is we we've been able to
we can move the camera
we have the capacity to move the camera
which is a big thing and that's why i
did it
i focused on that so much back in that
period of time when i was an
entrepreneur
i mean explicitly it was part of my
senior thesis when i was in college was
exactly that
how to move the camera from the
oppressors to the to the hidden
victories right if you want the first
move you have to make is you have to
change the underlying topology of the
media landscape if you haven't done that
nothing else is going to work once
you've done that there's a lot more to
do but at least you've got a chance
all right the second is we have to
re-learn how to tell the truth
that may be all actually move the camera
and re-learn how to tell the truth and
if i tell the truth i mean it in both
directions right on the one hand it's
the direction to express the truth and
to speak
with honesty and integrity and clarity
to the degree to which you can right to
tell the truth as a skillful practice as
well as an integrity practice
and to discern the truth to tell when
truth is being told
right to to on your as a listener to be
able to
listen clearly and to notice when what
you're hearing is
poorly spoken truth and support be
making that better spoken
and notice when what you're hearing is
in fact skillfully spoken lies
i notice and how to get that out of the
way right so to learn how to tell the
truth is a collective process
of of of development of parenting of
friendship of
of unconditional love that crucible of
growing those two pieces right that it
move change the underlying topology of
the media landscape so we can move the
camera to the
to the scapegoats and the second is
re-learn how to tell the truth
get those two things right and we
probably have everything we need
tell the truth what does that mean tell
the truth does that mean
telling the truth about fake news
because fake news and mythology are the
same thing
right fake news is the vestige of
mythology fake news
is the vestige of being able to shape
events and represent them in a narrative
which is dishonest which doesn't tell
the truth which puts little scare words
around joe rogan joe rogan the
alt right blah blah blah you know that
whole thing that's what people that's
mythology and it's vested
little pieces of it are still there
they're still in us right we're still
we're still holding on to that those
shards of uh
mythic lies that get us to i'll give you
i'll give you a few pieces because i
think there's a this is a whole um
there's a whole practice it's a whole
discipline in the sacred sense that
perhaps
in many ways maybe the most sacred sense
um
let me do some sort of simple ones first
and maybe do a deeper one after that
because
it feels to me like it's going to take a
little while to get the deeper thing to
settle into clarity
if at all um one of the things that i
noticed
when i uh started creating some youtube
videos
and i should be very clear the the
i don't know how many youtube videos i
created maybe 30 and then now i've got
this friend of mine who's
my friend's son is just creating more
out of some videos i've done probably
one out of this because this that thing
just
bits in this conversation so my um you
know i was writing
on medium if you wrote a oh 50 articles
there
and i got to the point where it was just
a lot of work and
um i felt like it was more work than it
was worth
so my wife said well why don't you just
say it in a video maybe you could just
record yourself saying it because you
say it you know you talk to people all
the time
why don't you just record it and then
just share it so that's what i did right
that was that was the beginning of the
end of the whole thing
all right now one of the things i
noticed
and it came in two flavors was there was
clearly a deep sense
a fundamental assumption that if you're
expressing yourself
at all in public you must be endeavoring
to build a brand
that if you are not be being a good
marketer
then you've already missed the boat
right to say something insightful
it can only be valuable in the context
of building your brand and i said in the
sense of like people come to me and say
um you're saying interesting things but
you're not going to get a million
viewers if you don't do x y and z like
those kinds of assumptions right
the objective is to get a lot of
attention ideally attention you can own
and presumably monetize i don't know
about that part
so that's one side the other side was
very similar even but even more powerful
which was a anger at my failure for
having done so
so one side was kind of like a hint
i assume that you're trying to build a
brand and here's how you're not doing it
well the other side is actually anger
for not doing a better job
at at building a brand it being whatever
the right marketing having good
marketing
so one thing would be to dig into that
and disabuse yourself
of that as an unconscious assumption and
bias right to tell the truth
is to orient towards the relevant not
towards the salient
to use verbacy's language which is good
language and a man who does a very good
job at this
that doesn't mean to be obscure i
apologize
publicly right now for the degree to
which my speech has been obscure
i i admit a significant lack of
skillfulness in communicating the kinds
of things i'm trying to communicate
clearly and i've endeavored over
decades to do so you should have seen me
15 years ago
um doesn't mean to endeavor to be
obscure by no means right clarity is
part of being able to tell the truth if
you're not speaking clearly then you're
also doing it poorly
but to speak seductively is also to do
it wrong so
seductive simplicity seductive
obfuscation
and truculent obfuscation are all errors
in telling the truth
so to build skillfulness and expression
which is able to orient towards the most
relevant
towards the most insightful that's
another one that's one here's another
one and this is actually going deeper
the truth is not propositional
those who read the book should know this
more than anyone else the words are not
the truth
right i cannot convey the truth to you
by telling you a story
in in the words the words if you take
the words and you separate them from the
thing that
motivated those words to be spoken in in
the fashion that they were
will be lost and as soon as you copy it
once you've lost something
very deep
the truth is to be found in that thing
which coordinates and
and ordin ordinates the words to be the
ones that are selected
in the or in the in the in the
orientation that they're selected
there's a generator function there's a
transcendent essence there's a
truth is transcendent right there's a
thing that cannot be said that
nonetheless is the thing that is
expressed
i must speak it for you to hear it right
i must draw it for you to see it
but we can both perceive it in the
transcendent and what i'm trying to do
when i speak and when i draw
is to give you hints to orient you into
this
in your own mode of perception such that
we are suddenly both perceiving the same
transcendent object in the way that we
do
and then to coordinate us so the
speaking is not in the words the words
are a protocol
a way to create a communications channel
so that we can become coordinated in our
mutual perception of the transcendent
that is another deep deep thing to learn
to tell the truth right to learn to
become
a communications channel to learn to
actually actually achieve fidelity with
each other
and to mutually perceive the
transcendent in a shared way
that is the deepest or a very deep sense
of that
it reminds me of the johnny cash uh song
um
about the man in black you know and he
says um
there's there's a line there that he
says that i think
kind of puts this into contrast for us
that there is a false transcendence
and the false transcendence again is the
domain of the sacred of of the scapegoat
mechanism
the shared transcendence that people
feel let's say let me give you an
example stanley pawns and martin
fleischmann you know those names
yep why is stanley pons hiding in france
to this day
let me just think about that for a
second
stanley ponds has gone off the grid for
decades since 1989 when him and martin
martin fleischmann passed away
that he was one of the world's best
chemists martin fleischmann
so you have stanley ponds and martin
fleischmann and they come out with this
announcement that they have created what
they believe to be cold
fusion
and to this day we have an american
stanley pons who has renounced his u.s
citizenship and has been in france and
obscurity
since and hiding just he was so ashamed
and vilified
now that's the christ story
it's not the complete story he was
there's no vindication he still
he's still i mean as we're speaking
there's a man who tried to do something
and i think he was earnest yeah and i
think they made mistakes
but he was vilified by the high priest
because he touched the holy of holies he
said
here is a here's a nuclear reaction and
they said you said nuclear you're a
chemist we're physics let's talk to you
come to my office we are the physicists
we outrank you in the jungle book
okay because we have the sacred fire we
created the bomb
you just use the word nuclear you come
to our office immediately
and all of the institutions and mit and
all the different media
sycophantically they raised them up like
a god at first the media did
and then they tore them down as soon as
the high priest said like caiaphas
it's better that they die than the whole
nation perish if the integrity of
nuclear science
is destroyed that's what they did
there's a man right now who did a
tabletop experience that produced excess
heat and has been replicated by other
people
for decades since also hanging out in
the hinterlands of the scapegoat
and we're not allowed to have a
conversation about it in polite society
why is that and what does that tell us
about the way
our bodies of knowledge are structured
there's a man in france
why we talk about science as a domain of
intelligence
the domain of rationality there's a man
in france who is disgraced for doing an
experiment
what about that at all sounds rational
what about that process yes
like the highest order of human
you know togetherness or human
understanding that that
that sounds like old-fashioned religion
to me that sounds like somebody just
somebody spoke out a line and said i
don't agree with your model of the
trinity and they said
beat it you're done get out
and by the way we need to make sure that
nobody else shows up any
big like you so you gotta be real done
right and to this day if you type in
it's now called
lenr low energy nuclear reactions or
whatever
there are still little groups in the
shadows working on it
and every now and then you'll get an
article in a third tier science magazine
maybe oh there's something there those
crazy people are doing who knows maybe
who knows but
but wait a second you know the premise
that you could create
nuclear type energy in a tabletop device
isn't that the biggest story in mankind
history i mean isn't that what
but no one's talking about it we're
talking about uh you know
this is the generalized thing so let me
let me um if you if you don't mind can i
hold two points
sure all right so the first point is
um the the scapegoats who have been
wandering in the wilderness we need to
be
we need to love them unconditionally and
by that i mean in the crucible
right so because they're going to be
they're going to be up
there's going to be a lot of damage
right it ain't easy to walk alone in the
wilderness
and it's even worse so i mean both in
terms of they will have emotional
developmental issues right and i and i
am among them so i know
of what i speak and i'm not i'm not sort
of pointing another folks and i spend a
lot of time with these kinds of people
they're
the kinds of people who i like is
another thing
they'll have actually had to be without
a community thinking about things in
their own private language in their head
which is they're going to have usually a
very odd language they use words
differently
than other people next to them use words
because they've been using their own
words for a long time
and they may actually have concepts that
are
four five seven levels of conceptual
complexity deeper
than we're typically using right because
we're we stand on the
shoulders of giants which means that we
tend not to think too hard about those
what those giants did
if you've been out in the wilderness
you've been thinking about um
you know einsteinian riemannian
manifolds
and you're like you know what there's
this branch this little this other
approach that was being thought about
in 1487 i'm going to take that branch
and you may have built something up
right well there's going to be nobody
who has a clue
right and they're going to be very
confused and maybe a little angry at you
just because it's hard to understand
what you're talking about right so would
you be very mindful of the fact that in
many cases there's going to be a
difficulty in communication
right and there's going to be emotional
fragility because they've been they're
used to being beat down they're used to
being yelled out they're used to being
not understood
and if they're holding something
valuable that's going to be even more
intense because they have a deep thing
that they've been trying to figure out
how to share with the world right so we
need to be
we need to be aware of that we need to
have compassion we need to actually
learn how to create
a context that is able to support them
in communicating and giving their gifts
back into the world
they're bumping up against the domain of
the sacred because they're challenging
the false transcendence that
if we're unified on this as settled
science
then together we can bind ourselves into
a corporeal body called
physics or whatever and we don't
question our forefathers we don't
question moses
we don't question feynman you know we
don't question
the the fathers of of these edifices
that we've built because we've done all
this empirical
experimentation and we have all these
equations and we have all these
credentials
we cannot afford to question hundreds of
years of
established inherited knowledge and and
to do so
is to bump up against that transcendence
that catharsis that out of body
experience that i
am a part of the of the of the communion
of what is called x physics or whatever
it is
and that's why they have to have that
vicious anger to excommunicate people
because they say
you're destroying you're destroying
reality itself you're destroying
our religion in israel all human beings
are designed to have worship
and religion you can't escape it right
you can't escape the sacred ah right
right right yes there's
so you're destroying our power and
you're destroying our religion
you're destroying our sense of unity and
togetherness
i don't like this physicist and this guy
doesn't like my thing but together we've
settled that
this is the way the atom is you see i
mean that's your that's how you bind
together and when someone comes along
and says
no the adam's not that way then the
shared togetherness of
no we hate each other except we come
together on these shared dogmas
and you're saying that dogma's not there
that means we have nothing to bind us
together
that's apocalyptic for people in all
fields of knowledge
all right so let's put into the second
point so this is an example of that
notion of thinking about money
differently or economics differently
i actually made this proposal to the
obama administration in 2008
which didn't go anywhere but i donated
meaningfully to the obama
campaign so i had got rich folk access
so i got to
talk to people um
so the proposal was this i said look we
currently spend
x i'm just gonna call it it's called 100
billion dollars we spend x
on science and you guys are about to put
dump a ton of money into the economy
remember what was it called
not tarp but the uh rebuilding america
infrastructure
bill what about cash for clunkers are
you
no well we might as well be the same
thing right and you're going to do a
terrible terrible job at it that's i'm
just going to tell you right now you're
going you're going to waste
trillions of dollars why don't we waste
trillions of dollars intelligently
like why don't we fail forward here's a
proposal
100 billion dollars a year for the next
four years
five years you know if you want to be
pretend like you're going to transcend
your your uh
being president for the first term
allocated into a platform
where every american citizen has the
ability to you know prove their
credentials get your social security
number wherever it happens to be get
your identity
and each american citizen is given a pro
rata share of that to allocate to any
scientific or engineering
endeavor that they see fit and so you
basically take that money and fully
decentralize it
and of course the first order thought is
well you got two problems one is people
don't know what they should be funding
people are dumb
the second is people will tend to be
there'll be some real corruption right
they will give money to their friends
and my response is number two yeah and
probably vastly less than is currently
being corrupted because they're not as
good at it as you guys are because
you've been at it for a while
and number one i'm not so sure
i i get the distinct sense and i i said
here's the here's the math right the
math looks like this
when you run an optimizing function on a
system that has can create niche
niche production it can maintain the
integrity of its own institutional
fabric
what you end up getting is you get
increasingly narrow deep uh
investigations right so i take a look at
physics and i can look at chemistry and
take a look at biology
it tends to have this root structure it
looks like a plant where i've got these
sort of
deep tap roots they go like that but if
i look between them there's these big
dark areas between these two roots right
so i've got real deep investigations of
increasingly esoteric areas
and vast territories in between that
aren't being investigated
if all i did was broke the structure
so the money was effectively random like
i literally said i don't care if it's
randomly allocated it could just be
randomly allocated
i would be willing to bet you would get
one full order of magnitude and possibly
two orders of magnitude
increase discovery in practical science
through this program right so that's an
example of the kind of thing like
you know what let's just use basic
sensibility when you've been going at
something for 50 or 60 or 80 years with
the same basic institutional structure
you could be damn sure that it's a bad
combination of corruption
and bureaucratic cowardice that focuses
on increasingly narrow and oftentimes
cover your ass like don't you know don't
investigate anything as long as what you
do looks like investigation
and if all you did was pop that thing
open and make that money available to go
decentralized
you get a 10x increase in performance
almost immediately my battery's about to
die so i've got to move
i think australia i think our time is up
too yeah yeah yeah
so and we could do that right that's not
that hard these days we have a technical
basis to make that extremely possible
if we could get the get the ear if one
can imagine a situation where
the this all right i'll go two pieces
and maybe we'll end on that
so right now we're not just wasting a
trillion dollars we're wasting ten
trillion dollars and probably more
and wasting wasting like seriously
massively wasting like to prop up the
too big to fail banks is
is an absurdity beyond comprehension um
you know if you think about in terms of
like parasitism and then
um no would it be
sophisticated enemies parasites and then
and then things that just aren't very
efficient
the banks are somewhere to the left side
of that continuum um
and there's certainly nowhere near uh
need to be around
all right so if i'm dropping 10 trillion
dollars into the economy just to stave
off deflationary spiral
maybe we could be a little bit more
clever about it we could actually do it
in
a new way and there's a lot of cool ways
you could do it right you could just
like i just said i could just create a
whole platform and say hey american
citizens here's what's going to happen
each of you are going to get 50 000 to
invest over the next
36 months and we're going to do it in a
cool digital way
and the way the investment works is it's
going to be like the uh you know the
work projects administration
you can't give it to yourself you got to
give it to some other project we create
a platform people create projects
everybody's going to get money that they
invest
the first move is you have to invest in
another project and yep there's going to
be some corruption
a lot less corruption than you see in
any other project that gets funded
through any existing bureaucracy but
we're going to get a level of creativity
the likes of which we haven't seen in
100 years
all right and maybe it's not 10 billion
maybe it's just a trillion maybe it's
just a trillion dollars
but think about it think about the
insanity all right that's one now
the naive part of that is not the
topology i just described and by the way
i can give you a topology which is
a hundred times more effective than that
we just sort of thought it through a
little bit
the naive part of that is not that's
apology obviously right the naive part
is to assume there are any ears to hear
at the top of the choice making
structure that would even vaguely
consider that as a thing to do
for about 50 different reasons that's
the second move right the second move is
we're going to go ahead and have to take
sovereignty back i got bad news for you
you're not going to be able to vote for
anybody and sort of ordinary voting
we may be able to continue to vote for a
while that may actually still have some
legitimacy
but it's not going to be a situation
where you're gonna a politician's gonna
come to you and make you a promise
you're gonna vote for that
we're gonna have to take sovereignty
back that's the only way this thing
happens the people are gonna have to
wake up and say whoa
we've been sitting around not doing
anything for a while jefferson and the
boys kind of did a good job and every
you know our friends back in the in the
1860s in the 1930s kind of
did a revved at this thing but at the
end of the day the buck stops here and
that here is right here
so we're gonna have to step in we're
gonna have to look around say they
aren't gonna say this and most of the
time when they say they're gonna save us
they're going to be screwing us
take responsibility back figure out what
the what a right right design looks like
execute on that design and either force
them to do it
or just do it ourselves and because the
end of the day like i talked to somebody
about this in terms of
like a big company let's say google
google's not real
there's no google there's a whole bunch
of people
who do things and they've agreed as
people to do things in a certain way
according to certain hierarchies and
certain rules and processes and that set
of agreements becomes the thing that we
know is google
those people change their agreements
they'd be doing something else
and google would no longer exist as a
viable entity
that's the whole country right the whole
country is every single thing you have
every
every structure that you think that you
see that is real is not real
it's people making choices and what
agreements they want to make
we can make new agreements we can always
do that that paul has always been rested
in the people sovereignty is that the
ability to make the choices that you
make and own the responsibility for
those choices
and to make the agreements that you want
to make i can tell you right now there
is no path through this does not go
through
us as a people reclaiming sovereignty
making the choices that we choose to
make to own the choices that we're
making
take responsibility again and
sovereignty is responsibility more than
anything else
and then be begin to make new agreements
and maybe we can execute on that through
the vote
right but if we do it it's gonna be more
like this it's gonna be uh
steve sorry man you're the one who's to
have to be the representative
because i you know you're kind of good
at that kind of thing here's the list of
things you're going to do
now your job is not to figure out what
to do we've already figured out what to
do
your job is just to make sure it gets
done and report back when it's done our
representative is going to be our
representative
not our boss all right now we're not
looking for them to
have ideas we're looking for them to
just get done if we vote at all
right so that's the last part right this
let's be
not naive that remember that first is to
recognize the wrongness second is to
feel powerless
third is to actually create an illusion
that's awake from our illusions we're
not powerless
we're just dis uncoordinated right we're
just
self powerless we pretend like we're
powerless because we haven't had the
courage
to fight a war right to have a warlike
disposition to have the commitment to
say okay
worst case scenario if we go in this
direction and by the way it's bizarre
worst case scenario
our standard of living gets cut in half
yeah things might get rough
which means that we return to like the
1980s standard of living
maybe i don't get an iphone 11 for
another 18 months instead of six months
come on um it will it'll be it'll
there's some some toughness but it ain't
seizing the beats of the beaches of
normandy toughness right so we're not
hopeless we're not helpless we're just
cowardly
we're just refusing to accept
responsibility for the whole of the
commonwealth
as soon as we recover from that
cowardice and choose to recognize that
the responsibility is where it always
has been at our own feet
and begin the process of saying all
right who's got ideas let's talk about
it
let's figure it out and live by the
rules you just mentioned
and just learn how to to tell the truth
stop trying to people
stop trying to get attention and stop
what is it
venkatesh rao wrote a really great
article on the internet of beefs
just exit the internet of beeps man
that's just silliness
stop playing in that game that's just a
stupid game it's a little lame it's a
dumb game
um be friends learn how to be friends
again
i learn how to engage in what it means
to be an ancient voluntary association
and it's funny the thing that i've
noticed over the past
two years and i've made a distinction so
there's a way of thinking about in terms
of team balloon team red
and i think that that distinction
creates a little bit of confusion and
more attention than it needs to
so i'm going to make a slightly
different distinction and some people
might be laughing when i say it
american distinction between between
team must have
and team nice to have and team must have
are the folks where if they decide to
leave
everything falls apart and there's a lot
of them we're seeing them right now in
the food chain
seemed nice to have for folks who if
they stopped if they stopped doing what
they did
either we wouldn't notice we'd be glad
you know we don't need those and that's
that's really an interesting thing
because
as i've noticed over the past two years
is when i have conversations with folks
who are on team must have
they tend to nod their head in what i'm
saying and if they disagree we're able
to disagree honestly
we can usually find a compromise that
works and usually it's a collaboration
that actually is a better solution
i think largely because if you if you
live your life actually having to solve
problems with nature
you know the way i've described in the
past is uh if the pipe bursts
do you grab a wrench do you call a
plumber
or do you call the supervisor if you
grab the wrench you tend to have a
certain set of capacities to figure out
how to solve problems with other people
because you're aware of the fact that no
matter how much you complain or whine or
control or manipulate
nature's nature you better just figure
out how to figure how to make it work
if you call the super that gets really
problematic
you use words like problematic because
most of the way you solve problems that
you figure out how to convince other
people to do the things you want to do
and that's a totally different game and
hard to collaborate in a space of people
who are optimized for manipulating other
people to do what they want to do
um so anyway so largely when i'm saying
what i'm saying i'm actually speaking to
team
must-have i'm not so much worried that
right now about team nice to have
because if team must have gets its act
together
looks around says we're gonna take
responsibility for this thing we're
gonna design it
we're gonna sign up for it we're gonna
accept the fact that it may be rough
maybe rough going for a little while
but we're going to go there we're going
to make it happen and we'll make an
offer to team nice to have to join
on the terms we've defined and they're
good terms right we're actually
it's a much better world we can get to
and we can get to the promised land in a
in a
old testament sense um
team nice to have is going to take those
terms pretty quick
so that's what i got about that that's
very good it's not going to come through
um government bureaucracy or
universities that have that power
because
that would be like henry ford trying to
position himself to introduce a new way
of transportation and at the time
there's a department of transportation
that says
excuse me what are we going to do about
the horseshoe makers we're the ones
running this bureaucracy
you said i mean if the horseshoe makers
are in charge of the department of
transportation they would never allow
the
the combustion engine and the automobile
to exist
and so we've got to stop asking
permission of the horseshoe makers of
reality
and just start creating the technology
that people need
yeah yeah every one of these
institutions was created by regular old
people
there's nothing out there that's created
by anybody who's radically smarter than
the people who are hanging out right now
so the the myth of the man is really
just us isn't it it's just the crowd
it's just people we're very good it's
been a pleasure talking to you jordan
it's
a wonderful conversation yeah very nice
to meet you sir
look forward to seeing what happens all
right take care bye